and we can go ahead and start. All
right, recording has started. I am now
letting everyone in. And uh just before
we start, Adrian, you're doing minutes.
Ishmael, you're doing mute, unmute. Am I
correct?
>> That's correct.
>> Yep.
>> Okay.
>> And are you leaving at 4?
>> Um if you I mean I I continue for this
meeting for the duration. It should be
okay.
>> Okay, cool. Because if if not, I can
take over after you.
>> Not a problem. Right, I am admitting
everyone.
Okay, good afternoon everybody. Uh I'm
Dominic Zerllo and I'm with the New
Mexico Department of Health Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin Programs and uh
we are uh going going ahead with our
next meeting for propagation uh with
Chris Piscus as the chair and uh so
Chris I oh and just as a reminder for
everybody is this meeting is being
recorded so we do ask that people watch
their language. Um, and part of the
reason why we do not have uh the cameras
on for most people and just for uh the
chair and some of the do staff is just
so that we can make sure that there is
enough bandwidth for everybody to stay
in the meeting as much as possible. What
we've just discovered because of the
popularity of these meetings, if we
allow cameras for everybody, we
sometimes have people dropping in and
out on a more frequent basis than
sometimes happens otherwise. Uh and then
the other reason is just to make sure
that there is nothing in the background
that is inappropriate for when we post
these meetings. We do post them on the
program and the advisory board's
website. And uh so if you've missed some
of the previous meetings, you are
welcome to go on back and view the
recordings. So and with that in mind, I
will turn it on over to Chris. So Chris,
uh back or back to you.
Thank you Dominic for uh as always for
everything you do for the program and
thank you to everyone who has um come to
this meeting. Um, I see a lot of names
that have been here quite a few times
and
like this time we'll have a moment for
introductions coming up soon, but I
always like to start my meetings off
with just a 30 seconds of silence to
kind of try to cultivate a small
container of of peace in a world full of
chaos and just uh bring ourselves to
center and and remind ourselves why
we're here. So um just 30 Second chance.
All right, thank you all. Um, and we're
going to go ahead and open it up for
people to introduce themselves. Please,
uh, let me know who you are. Uh, are you
from New Mexico? And if you have any
affiliations, remember if you want to
have a say in the voting during our
meeting at all, you need to introduce
yourself and be from New Mexico. So, um,
please start raising your hands and
introducing yourselves.
Okay,
Estavan,
I have enabled your microphone. Please,
when you're ready.
Good afternoon everyone. This is Stean
Hernandez, owner of New Mexico Fungi and
president of the New Mexico Micology
Guild.
>> Thank you very much for that Estan. Next
we have Denali. Denali, I have enabled
your microphone please when ready.
>> Hi chair. Hi um members of the
department. My name is Denali Wilson. I
am uh the director of strategic support
for the healing advocacy fund which is a
nonprofit that supports state regulated
access programs. I um I'm based normally
in Los Cusus but have been living the
last month in Santa Fe for the
legislative session which ends in less
than 24 hours and I am very excited for
that.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Ash Shelton. Ash, I have enabled
your microphone. Please, when ready.
>> Hello, I am Ashton. I born and raised in
New Mexico. Currently, manager of orange
and also on the board of Mexico.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Kohley. Is that is that I
pronounced that correctly? Please let me
know. I have enabled your microphone.
>> Oh, sorry about that. It's a Chay and
hi, it's nice to be here. I am the
founder and director of Miogen
Institute. I do not live in New Mexico.
I'm just very excited for what's going
on here and want to witness. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Shaylee. I
appreciate that and for the correction
there. I'll keep that a um next
[laughter]
>> Next we have John. Uh
I have enabled your microphone. Please
go ahead.
>> Hi, I'm uh Jonathan Eick. Um I've lived
here in New Mexico for the last 18
years. Currently here in Albuquerque and
I'm a home micologist. I've done some
work with Mexico
and I'm just here to help any way I can.
>> Fantastic. So you might have cut out a
little bit there. I don't know if anyone
else caught that. Uh
it it's no matter we have next on the
list we have John S. John I have enabled
your microphone please go ahead.
Just a reminder John to unmute yourself
you have to uh click on the microphone
icon on the top right of your screen. Uh
that way you can unmute yourself and Oh
I think I see it there.
>> Thanks. Got it. My name is John Star.
Our organization is called Strong
Medicine. We're based here in
Albuquerque um in New Mexico and we're
just excited about the bill and and
willing wanted to participate any way we
can.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have James. James, I have enabled your
microphone please when ready. Hey James
Blackford, New Mexico resident uh for
about 20 years. Super excited about the
program. um personally seen the benefits
to psilocybin mushrooms and um yeah just
uh love the work everybody's doing and I
definitely appreciate y'all.
Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Jim. Gym when ready.
[snorts]
Jim, just as a reminder, if you're
having any difficulty there, uh just uh
take a look at if you unmute yourself,
uh you have to on the top right there's
a microphone icon. If you click that, uh
that will unmute yourself. If you're
still finding trouble, um that's no
matter. we can come back to you at a
later point and uh we can try to get
that introduction done. Uh in the
meantime, I shall continue onwards to
Chris. Chris Guest, I have enabled your
microphone. Please begin when ready.
Hello, I'm Chris Guest, New Mexico
native and resident uh owner of Four
Corners Fungi, vice president of the New
Mexico Micology Guild and associate
professor at UNM.
Thank you very much for that, Chris. And
uh next we have Lisa Ginsburg. I have
enabled your microphone. Lisa, please
begin when ready.
>> Hello everyone. Uh my name is Lisa. I'm
the founder of Chunga Institute and I am
not a citizen of New Mexico.
>> Thank you very much for that. We're
going to try and get back to Jim. Um let
me just take a look. I think he messaged
in the chat if I'm correct. Uh, unmute
is grayed out. Okay, let's take a look
at what we can do there. What I will do
is I'll disable and then reenable. That
might sometimes does the trick. So, I
have reenabled your microphone. I don't
know if you can see that. Um, does the
unmute option show for you now?
Okay. Okay. Well, in that case, Jim,
what I'd recommend is if you drop off
the call uh and then join back in. Often
it's the case that sometimes there might
be an occasional little issue here and
there. Uh but sometimes it's a simple
case of just jumping off the call and
then jumping back on and we can try and
get that matter resolved. All right.
Okay. Uh without further ado,
back to you, Chris.
>> Excellent. Thank you all for
um joining and introducing yourselves.
Um I encourage all of you to be active
participants in this process. Um I
definitely want to make this you know a
communal process. So please be your most
courageouselves and find your voices if
you have something to say when we're
going through this uh agenda um or
through this process rather. So uh
Dominic's posted the agenda up.
[clears throat] This is a a piece of you
know this is just a piece of paper. So,
I'm always flexible on this stuff. If we
need to go down a rabbit hole or
something, we will. I might change the
order up a little bit. Since we have uh
some people here early that um may get
pulled into stuff with the legislative
session, I move item E up uh to the
front of the list. Um but yeah, this is
what we're going to talk about today.
And
um now can we pull up the outline
Dominic?
>> Uh switching over now.
>> And can I call on
um like I said, first thing we're
probably going to do is go back over
some sunset clause alternatives. Since
we had to remove our sunset clause last
week, I wanted to invite Denali Wilson
up to speak about some alternatives. If
you're ready, Denali
>> and just before you talk, Denali, I just
want to make sure can uh people see the
document?
>> We can. Well, I can on my end. I'm
>> a few others. I I'm seeing some other
thumbs up. Okay, perfect. Thank you.
Thank you everybody.
>> Fantastic. And just uh before we begin,
I believe um our guest has returned to
the chat. Um
just want to quickly find them. I'm sure
I just admitted them.
Okay, so Jim,
let's see uh if we can
I seem to have lost them. I don't know
where they gone. Okay, no worries. All
good.
when he comes back if if he
we'll just give him another opportunity
when he when he gets back in here if we
can.
>> Absolutely.
>> Excellent. Um
>> no, I think it was Jim Jim Dodson,
correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Okay. I I see him.
>> Oh, yes. I see. Oh, there he is. Yeah.
Okay. Uh
so, your microphone has been enabled,
Jim.
Um
do give it a go if we can.
Still grayed out. Ah uh that may be uh
an issue on potentially your end. Go
ahead Dominic.
>> Yeah. So Jim that you if it's grayed out
that means there is not a microphone
connected. So for whatever reason on
your system a microphone is not showing.
Um, I will tell you I experienced that
earlier myself with a headset. So
sometimes for whatever reason they may
not connect to your system, but there's
if you want to try troubleshooting it
there on your end a little bit, we will
give you another opportunity down the
road if you would like.
All right.
Thank you, Jim. Sorry. Thank you for
your patience. Um,
Denali, are you able to
are you ready to come on? [laughter]
>> Yeah. Hi. Uh, thank you, chair. Um, I
want to mention to Josh uh Josh Capel
who's policy council for the healing
advocacy fund is also on the call. Um,
and him and I had a discussion and he
may be able to to add to this
conversation. Um, I'll I'll start by
saying reintroducing myself. My name is
Denali. I [clears throat] um maybe
didn't mention in my intro, but in I I'm
a lawyer and a policy advocate and
sometimes wear that hat and wanted to
wear that in um service of this
conversation um around residency and the
the sunset clause that was proposed.
Um, I I also want to apologize for not h
being able to contribute to the
conversation earlier. I know that there
were previous conversations about it and
we're reviving it. So, sorry to have
been um late to contribute, but I I'm
grateful for the opportunity now. Um,
Dominic, do you is are there is anyone
from the legal department on this call
by chance? No, Denali, they they are not
at this time, but I can relay
information to them and they've also
provided me with some additional
information in preparation.
>> Okay, great. And I mean, we really do
want to be a resource not just to the
subcommittee, the advisory board, but to
the department um in in tackling some of
these emerging legal issues. So
certainly if there's an opportunity to
have uh an individual conversation with
the the legal department, we'd love we'd
love that um in any way.
Um,
so I I I wanted to start out by saying I
and maybe this has been a part of the
conversation
previously, but um, from my perspective,
I I think there is a sense in this
community that we want to be as
protective as is legally possible. Um
and and that comes both from a pride
that we have as a state in protecting um
in protecting those business interests
um and also I think on the heels of what
has been uh a turbulent cannabis
recreational roll out especially as it
comes to outside business interests. I
think those are are big factors at play
in the conversation here. Um, and the
residency requirement really
centers around what is the dormant
commerce clause. So, just to to explain
for people, the federal government has
exclusive authority to regulate
interstate commerce. And so, what the
dormant commerce clause says is that
states can't, right? States can't
regulate interstate commerce because
that's the exclusive authority of the
federal government. Um, but the thing
that I I think is really important for
this conversation and what I'd love to
have a a a deeper conversation with the
legal department at DOH if possible is
that that there's a circuit split on
this issue as it as it pertains to
residency and state plant medicine
programs. And so um while you know we
have two circuits, the first and the
second that have shot down residency in
cannabis programs, the ninth circuit,
which is also the most recent case, has
said, and I I think this is is kind of
intuitive as we're talking about federal
authority, that the dorm dormant
commerce clause analysis really doesn't
make sense because the interstate
commerce that we're talking about is
federally illegal. So the the the
analysis of federal authority really
doesn't hold weight. Um and that that is
the ninth circuit which I'll I'll
mention too. You know New Mexico when
we're picking circuits if we don't have
one in the 10th where we where we are
and and there isn't a 10th circuit case
we tend to follow the ninth circuit over
the second and the first and and I think
there would be an opportunity to do that
here. Um, and in general, just what a
circuit split is, when we're we're when
a legal question is un unresolved, it's
an opportunity to make a choice. And
here that choice I I I believe should be
to protect growers as as best that we
can. Um, I'll say two additional
considerations for residency.
one that a residency requirement that's
2 years or less and and I think we're
we're close to that window. It's just so
unlikely that it would be challenged
because the the process of litigation is
much slower than it is for a business to
actually establish reg residency
um in in a state. Uh and so I think the
as proposed the the sunset date for this
residency was January 1, 2029 and with a
program launch at the end of this year
that that seems to be within that
window. And the other consideration
I
you know cannabis is for a million and
one reasons just very different than
than psilocybin. I want to I want to I
want to highlight that I I just my
expectation is that this is not going to
be as ligious of a of a group than
cannabis because there just honestly is
not the kind of money to be made that
fuels um that fuels the kind of
litigation around residency
requirements. So um those are the those
are those considerations.
Um I I think the other thing that the
department could consider if we don't
want to permit a residency requirement
um is is a grower um or is a cap for
grower licenses because if the
department caps licenses that then
allows the department to create their
own merit-based light license system and
we could there very easily give
preference to people with growing
experience in New me or for example um
people who've paid taxes the previous
year in New Mexico and that I think
provides the protective factors that
that folks are really looking for.
Um
and and then just in general, right, the
the issue with residency and the the
legal issue is around not discriminating
against outofstate businesses with all
of the nuance that I just provided. Um
but there is nothing that prohibits the
state from incentivizing
New Mexico growers. So again, if we're
not if we're not willing to
um move forward with a residency
requirement,
um we should really be prioritizing any
available incentive opportunities. I
think uh you know potentially
partnership from the state department of
agriculture or other state programs
would be a really great way, right? The
problem is discrimination against
outofstate business opportunities, but
that doesn't apply to any kind of
incentives that we could provide to New
Mexico growers.
And I think that's all that I do want to
ask if it's okay with you, chair, to see
if if Josh Capel, who's on the call,
have anything to add or amend from from
my [clears throat] summary.
>> Yes, please.
Josh, do you have anything to add?
>> Hi all and and thank you very much. Um,
my name is Josh Kappa. I'm an attorney
licensed in in Colorado and um a policy
director with the Healing Advocacy Fund.
And I and I think Denali, you know,
really um summed it up quite nicely. I
think there is the only thing I'd add is
that there's a distinction um legally
between durational residency
requirements versus current residency
requirements and you know requiring
someone to be a resident of New Mexico
for two years versus requiring someone
to be a resident of New Mexico if
they're holding the license. And there
might be some way to play with current
residency requirements versus durational
to accomplish, you know, similar similar
goals.
And that is all I have. But thank you
guys very much.
>> Thank you Josh for for coming on and
sharing with us and thank you Denali for
that update. Um
Dominic, do you want to say anything on
this? Do you have any thoughts so far?
>> Yeah, I mean I can I can just say and
and I appreciate the the comments from
Denali. I will say that our our our
attorney uh for the department did
actually expressly state that they did
believe that the dormant uh uh commerce
clause the dormcy commerce clause did
apply in this and that because even
though there is a circuit split if there
was any um legal action that did occur
that could actually stall and actually
potentially stop the program from
continuing forward as Well, um, but we
did experience that with regard to
cannabis. And while I appreciate the
thoughts cuz we we all want to think
that everybody always has best of
intentions. And I do believe that
everybody that we have worked with so
far at this time does have that.
However, that doesn't mean that other
individuals who do not necessarily have
those best of intentions would not enter
into the scene and that could create and
cause additional issues. But um our
attorney did say that they did believe
that the commerce clause does apply and
that with that that we would not be able
to have that kind of a residency
restriction on it. Um now as far as the
incentives I think that's a great idea.
Um, and we've actually talked about that
before, uh, including, I believe in one
of these meetings it came up. Might have
been one of the other committees though,
pardon me because we've had so many. I
can't remember exactly which one, but
about incentivizing and [snorts] I don't
I think that that's a great idea. We
just do not have the resources or funds
through the department in order to be
able to do that at this time. Um, and so
if there are other ideas on how to do
that, that would be phenomenal. And um I
think that could actually be um that
portion could actually be done either
way regardless of whether or not there
is a residency clause or not.
>> All right. So,
so you're saying that
your legal team is adamantly opposed to
the residential clause even though New
Mexico may follow
um
you know closer with the 10th circuit
ideation on this um
and that DO doesn't have the resources
to set up a
uh
something that would help our growers.
>> An incentive program.
Um
what would what would DOH need for to
set up an an incentive program? I I
don't see that as being that taxing of a
process.
It it would just be in addition to the
permitting process to
to check that they've paid taxes the
last couple years, right?
>> Well, that wouldn't be an incentive
program. an incentive program would be
for example uh saying offering um unless
I'm misunderstanding what Denali means
by that and I'd be happy to defer to her
with regard to it but it would be
something like offering um instate um
you know organizations or companies you
know some sort of financial bonus or uh
incentive in order to be able to start
up um whether it be uh say for example a
small grant that sort of a thing in
order to be able to start and we just do
not have that. But if there's some other
idea behind as far as for an incentive,
we'd be very happy to hear it.
>> I think I think the idea was that we
limit the number of permits and give pre
uh we we allow people that have paid
taxes the last two years dibs at those
at those
incentives basically or those permits.
So from a permit limitation that
actually we have lots of experience with
having lawsuits with regard to limiting
permits. So that really is not something
that we're looking at at this time
because that would create an issue. Um,
and while Denali is correct, if we were
to do some sort of a situation like
that, we could set up essentially like a
request for proposal sort of situation
and actually review score uh the
applications that come on in. However,
that has its own uh issues and
situations and we did go through that
for many years under cannabis and it was
problematic for everyone including for
the patients because prices were quite
frankly artificially driven higher due
to that limitation.
Uh and there are a couple of people who
have put things in the chat and I just
want to say that uh the first one to
Chris regarding the bill mandates that
psilocybin be grown in the state. That
is correct. Um it's not just even within
the bill but because psilocybin cannot
cross state uh borders uh due to its
schedule one uh level except for
research purposes in very small uh
situations or few situations but um
otherwise they cannot legally cross
state borders. So that is correct. Um
and then as far as priority for
licensing from Estavon, as far as that,
as far as incentives, first of all,
there are no program fees. So there
would not be a way to reduce program
fees. If there were, that would indeed
potentially be a way that we could do
incentive. Um and as far as for
prioritizing licensing, it really will
be again if there's no limit with regard
to licenses, then uh the licensing is
simply going to be in order submitted
quite frankly. Um and uh and similar to
that uh to Greg's question is that the
legislation does not currently allow us
to actually charge fees and part of that
from the beginning was to keep this as
affordable as possible.
Uh just to let you know we have a hand
up Denali with their hand up. Uh please
Denali go right ahead.
>> Hi. Um thank you and Dominic. I really
appreciate this conversation. Um I I do
continue to think it may be helpful if
we could have an opportunity to to talk
with the legal team. Um, I think
especially as you were responding to
Chris's message about outofstate about
the mushroom having to be grown in
state, that's exactly the reason that
the Ninth Circuit said, "Why are we
talking about the dormant commerce
clause?" Like, "This isn't interstate
commerce. It can't cross lines."
>> So that it's irrelevant. And I know that
right that that is that there right
there is a circuit split. So it makes
sense for the legal team to be risk
averse and and doing what is the most
taking the position that is um perhaps
the most the most um the least likely to
to result in litigation. And there is a
a strong desire from community to to
figure out if there is some protective
way for for us to move forward to
protect uh New Mexico growers. I'm
curious. So you you mentioned Dominic
that it that licensing would be like
first come first serve. Is there any
flexibility or willingness to
um prioritize licenses for local
residents
like create that kind of priority
system?
Uh well Denali once the the rules are in
place and the application process opens
uh it is open to all potential lences
and so uh because it's public at that
time and so once that becomes public
then any individuals or organizations
can apply um now what I would say is
individuals who are watching the process
who uh are paying attention during the
rule making would actually have
regardless would have an advantage to it
because they would know pretty much
exactly what was coming up and be able
to have applications ready to be able to
submit and be prepared so that as soon
as the applications open, they'd be able
to apply. But we can't there's not a way
to uh delionate between instate versus
out of state because we'd essentially
have to review the applications to make
that determination. And so it will be as
they come in, we will be actually
reviewing those applications as they
come in to make that determination.
I
>> think we have another guest with their
hand up.
Is it who I can't see his name.
>> Uh John S.
>> John S.
>> Hi. Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yes, we can hear you, John.
>> Thank you to both of you. I had a
question. Um, that's been in my mind for
a minute. I heard Dominic, you say no no
no limitating no limitations on permits
and then I was just listening to the
conversation about, you know, if you're
paying attention on these, you'll
understand what's going on and you may
be the first ones to to apply for these
permits. Now, what I'm what I'm trying
to understand is um, for an example,
like so say you know, you go and you
propose and you fill out all the
paperwork at RLD, for example, a liquor
license, right? and you meet all of the
criteria, all of your boxes are checked
and you pay your fees um and your your
application is approved, you get a
license. Um do you see that as a
parallel or more so where um there'll be
a limitation like okay in the first time
we're going to give out six permits or
we're going to give out 12 permits and
that's because I heard the first come
first serve type thing. Is that the
mentality? Or if you're there waiting in
line and your ducks are in a row and
your boxes are checked and you have you
meet all the criteria, pay your fees,
you'll be awarded a permit.
>> Right. So, John, that's a a great
analogy. And yes, essentially that is
what is happening. If there is an
organization that meets all of the
qualifications, they would then be
issued a permit. Now that will include
of course having you know not just a
review of the application but site visit
um which happens in many other
application processes as well and so uh
we'll be as those applications come on
in those would get scheduled as quickly
and as soon as possible we'll include
approximate timelines as we do for other
applications. We always put in
approximate timelines within the
application itself so that people aren't
just waiting to go wait I haven't heard
anything it's been 2 weeks you know this
way people have an idea of where they
are in the process uh and and go through
that does that help
>> thank you yeah that's very helpful
because after watching you know the
cannabis um licenses come out initially
and being a witness to that um it was a
big clarification or delineation I
really thought was important to make
about folks that are investing and and
creating situations to get ready for
this application process um only to be
feel like all the boxes are checked yet
not get a permit. So that that's very
helpful and I appreciate it.
All right. Um,
so this is a conversation I feel like
should continue, but uh maybe we need to
get the legal team together with uh the
micology guild and some of our folks
from Healing Advocacy Fund. Um, is there
a willingness to how can we make that
happen, Dominic?
Uh well, as it's already been requested
and I've uh requested potential dates
where they would be able to be
available. Right now, the main reason
why they're not able to is due to the
legislative session quite honestly. So
hopefully I will hear back uh with some
potential dates for that and we can see
about setting that up.
>> Okay.
As far as our proposals to the advisory
board, then should we put a placeholder
in that? I I feel like I kind of messed
up this last set meeting because we
overwhelmingly approved the sunset
clause in our
propagation outline here. And then I I
allowed a vote to kind of revoke that
and it was barely passed. Um, and I I
feel like that was a mistake given that
we we kind of gave them that, you know,
entryway already to continue that
conversation. And does that make sense,
Dominic?
>> I would say that when it goes to the
board, it can be that the committee, you
know, we explain it just as you did now,
Chris, that, you know, there was an
initial vote and then there was a
secondary vote and leave it to the board
at that point. But please remember uh
and this was for everybody on the call
is that um when it comes down to it,
these are recommendations and uh it it's
very important that the recommendations
are there. Um, however, the final
versions of the rules may not
necessarily have all of the
recommendations in them. And some of
them may be due to this type of legal
issues, such as the attorney saying,
"Sorry, this is just not going to work.
If we do this, there is too much risk
and that they consider too much risk
from a legal standpoint." So, um, so it
could be presented to the board with
both options, um, and to move forward
that way.
Okay. So, I'm going to continue pursuing
the meeting with the legal team and the
representatives from the healing
advocacy fund and the micology guild.
Um, Estebon, how do you feel about all
this right now?
>> Uh, thank you, Chris. And first off, I'd
just like to really thank Denali and
Josh for coming in and sharing all this
wonderful information with us today and
the department for being willing to
continue this conversation. Um really
the the spirit of the sunset clause is
truly to protect New Mexico residents.
Something I think we all ethically and
morally stand behind. But as we all know
these things that are often ethically
and morally correct are often not the
easiest way to go about things. So I
really appreciate the willingness to
continue an open conversation and I do
want to let you all know that uh myself
and the other members of the micology
guild are more than willing to
participate in any other meetings,
discussions or provide any additional
details we can to champion and support
this. So, thank you all very much.
>> Thank you, Estavan.
And I think you you hit on a really
great point and just to to bring it is,
you know, we're trying to figure out
what the best program is going to be for
everyone involved. Um, and I do think,
you know, Chris, uh, there's a couple of
comments in the, uh, in the chat just to
sort of go on it is, uh, you know, that
Chris has the comment about if we follow
the same trend as Oregon, there's going
to be a very small financial investment
for out of state companies to start a
business here. And that's another aspect
of this. You know, we are talking in
many ways about what are the legal
chances, the possibilities of things
occurring, of suits being filed, that
sort of thing. But the reality is is we
really have great communities here in
New Mexico regarding this. And you know
the I think in many ways that it's it's
a point of trying to ensure that that
that community support is there
regardless of you know who is allowed to
get a permit who is not allowed to get a
permit. A lot of it comes down to, you
know, are we supporting our local
communities? And that's actually part of
why I had proposed with the idea of
having a statement on the product
information document regarding the
number of years that a business has been
established in New Mexico so that people
can support local businesses and really
do so. And that way that brings it to
look, we want to make sure that
everybody knows what organizations and
companies are local New Mexico
businesses and which ones are not. And
that way that helps to support them
without necessarily running a foul of
the potential legal issues with circuit
splits and everything else.
I hope that helps to make sense because
we truly really do want this to be a New
Mexico focused um you know program.
>> No, thank you Dominic. And I think we'll
that's a good segue into our next
portion. So we'll we'll continue to work
the sunset clause through other avenues
and I will be bringing it up again at
the advisory board meeting on the 27th.
Um
but uh for now I think we can table that
conversation in committee and move on to
our next session section
[snorts]
um where we're going to section seven
food preparation and product handling.
So I can't see the document on my screen
so I'm in two different places. So,
there seems to be a little disconnect.
Just
>> I'm I'm about to put it into the chat
also.
>> Okay, cool.
>> Pardon me. Before we continue, just a
quick one. Uh I believe there was a hand
up. Uh it's gone down now, but uh
whoever had their hand up, uh John uh
John S. uh please uh go ahead. Your your
microphone has been enabled.
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. I just was
hoping for some sort of clarification.
did not participate in the meetings that
um began this conversation around the
sunset clause and residency um being
involved in many New Mexico business
over the years. Um, are we talking about
the duration of residency for say
principles of a company individually
that have resided in New Mexico for a
long time and as we know many people
start new companies all the time to
start new endeavors and so establishing
the age of per say a company is that
we're talking about or they say
principles of a company and how long
they've had residency in the state.
>> It actually was both John.
>> Okay. Thank you.
That concludes all questions.
>> All right, I think we have another one
in the chat. Um, but this is going back
to
um
>> I could read them out. Uh, two
questions. Uh, James Blackfall, uh,
Blackford, two questions. I don't see
any particular criteria as to what would
be approved as a grow site. For example,
does it have to be a standalone
building? Is a space in a home
considered adequate for a grow space
that would qualify for a permit or would
that be an automatic denial? It would be
a good it would sorry it would be good
to have uh what would be an acceptable
site explained so that we could uh so so
that there could be another check mark
on that a grower could prepare for as I
do not see anything in the current doc
that specifies that other than a secure
location to store product. Sorry that
was meant uh sorry that was the one
question the other one I answered as I
was typing
and I Oh, go ahead. Go ahead, Chris.
>> So, I think it is kind of laid out where
it talks about zoning requirements, but
remember these are initial
recommendations. So, you your group
would have to meet um light industrial
zoning requirements, I believe, is what
we kind of put in there. Um, but zoning
requirements of the local government
that you operate in. Um,
did you have something else to add to
that, Dominic?
>> You know, you pretty much covered it,
Chris. And so what that really means is
in most uh places, for example, uh as
long as the locality, the location
allows for that within its zoning and
the different zoning requirements are
different in different municipalities,
counties, things like that. So, as long
as it is acceptable in those counties,
then it could be done under those
conditions. But again, it would still
have to fit under, for example, in this
next section would still also have to
fit under environmental health, food
safety uh and handling trans uh training
certification. And so those sort of
things um is exactly a situation. So
yes, as you say in the the comment, yes,
it would uh fall back to the locality
with regard to that. Um, and then just
to answer Chris's, uh, yes, that is
actually a part of this current section
that we're reviewing that it would need
to have that certification with regard
to environmental health and food safety
um, to be able to do it, but not
necessarily a certified kitchen. Um, you
don't necessarily need a certified
kitchen to fit in that food safety, but
again, that is dependent upon the
locality.
>> All right. Well, and food preparation.
Back [laughter] to section seven. That
segus perfectly. Um, does anybody have
any comments on these basic rules for
food preparation and product handling?
Any ads
or thoughts here. Seems pretty standard
to me.
>> Uh, there is a hand up from Lisa. Is
that Sorry, I'm also squinting a little
[clears throat] to try to see all the
small.
Lisa, your mic is enabled.
>> Uh, thank you. So, I have one comment.
Uh, speaking with growers in Oregon and
Colorado, it became really clear that
there is a need for anyway for current
growers who already have functional
mushroom production established to be
able to integrate psilocybin production
in their current infrastructure as well.
Uh currently in Oregon and Colorado
that's not possible. A lot of these
people have quite expensive facilities
producing professional mushrooms for
gourmet restaurants and whole foods and
so on and it makes sense for them. They
already have established infrastructure
and I'm sure in New Mexico they already
you guys already have people who do
professional mushroom growing. um
allowing them integrate that lensure in
the infrastructure would be a huge
benefit. Um also in addition to food
processing creating edible products like
chocolates, gummies and so on that would
reduce cost significantly. Uh the second
comment would be considering enforcing a
limit on number of licenses to produce
mushrooms in big quantities of supply
and date. All you need is just one
reducer. Mushrooms grow really quick,
require less maintenance compared to
cannabis. So allowing
more than five licenses to the state
would lead towards businessing
businesses shutting down. So I would
also encourage you guys to explore that
as well. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you Lisa. And just to to note on
that with regard to the integrating into
current, there is nothing in our rules
uh that are being proposed right now
that would prohibit that and exactly for
the reasons that you mentioned. As far
as limiting the licenses, again, if we
do that actually opens the program up to
uh potential litigation and that's
actually a risk which we have seen
before uh through other programs and not
just cannabis. So, uh, if everybody
thinks it's all just we're just
comparing to compare can cannabis, it's
not. It's also happened in other areas.
Um, so what we do recommend and what we
would be recommending um, with regard to
um, from a licensing standpoint and for
anybody who looks at getting into a new
business quite frankly is to have your
business plan wellought out and
prepared. That's really the biggest
difference that helps organizations to
be successful in a new business and
that's going to be very important. We
have seen that of course anytime there
is a new field or a new business area
open up where businesses will open and
close um and we see it all the time for
example in restaurants it doesn't stop
just because of a few uh licenses and in
fact we end up hurting the field and uh
and again as I mentioned we have a lot
of experience in the past where limiting
licenses for a medication such as what
has happened with cannabis in multiple
states actually has ended up hurting
patients especially due to cost issues
and increased cost due to a an
artificial limit such as that.
Um and then as far as just edibles just
so that everybody knows all at this
current time for these initial rules
we've actually stated many times that it
will all of it will be homogenized and
will need to be in either powder or
capsule form. uh that we're not going
down the road of edibles at this time.
Um but that is on the table for the
future. It's just that aspect and the
additional issues that creates with
regard to licensing from a food
standpoint takes a lot longer to go into
and so to get the program started. We're
starting with that process and then
we'll continue to look at the other food
types or other edibles uh as the program
matures.
So, are we keeping this section in
specifically for that reason because
we're we're looking forward to the
program maturing?
>> No, it's still because it's an edible
product, you still have to do from a
food standpoint. So, you still have to
have those items. It's when you're
manufacturing food, so baking, cooking,
where it starts to become much more
complex as far as creating rules.
>> Yeah, just
>> I know we have another comment here. I
would like to just put in a quick plug
that um you know a lot of these
conversations have been had in the past
with regard to you know licenses and and
previous sub uh sections of this
document that we're working on. So I
want to try to bring us back in to focus
on the topic areas that we're covering.
Um, and if you kind of missed the boat,
uh, so to speak on on some of those
conversations, I want to make time for
us to have them in the future, but we've
already kind of decided those rags. So,
um, this might not be the best place uh,
considering we we've got a lot of work
to do before the board meeting next
week. So, let's go to Liz, but keep try
to keep that in mind that we're trying
to
trying to cover some ground here today.
Liz, did you have a question or a
comment?
>> Go ahead.
>> Oh, Lisa. Lisa, sorry.
Um yes, one more comment that came to my
mind in terms of packaging uh and
labelings on how facilitators would
package prepared food that uh clients
can consume during the session. Um
that's one of the biggest also questions
that was on a table in Oregon in terms
of some clients do lemon tucking tea
when they consume psilocybin as a dry
mushroom. Um
that can clients bring their own food
for the session. It's quite lengthy
experience. Six plus hours uh can be in
a healing center and if so if clients
would bring their beverages they water
does have to be prepackaged in
commercial packaging or they can bring
prepared food. I think that needs to be
also clarified and um written down in
the rules as well.
>> Thank you Lisa. that's actually a part
of the dosage and the administration
portion which is not a part of these
rules but that is actually something
that has already been discussed as a a
topic that needs to be raised as far as
food during that time period. So thank
you very much for that.
>> Okay.
So
going back to section seven, are there
any comments regarding this
area of the outline?
>> And just since it's been a little bit,
I'm going to put it in the chat again
just so that people can see it.
And again, this is really about the uh
that it has to any conversion of the
materials has to be subject to food
safety oversight. So through whether it
be environmental health, food safety
divisions depending upon the localities
and that there's not an exemption from
standard food safety requirements.
>> And essentially for now this just means
basically taking the the mushroom from
the substrate block, grinding it up into
a homogeneous product and then maybe
capsuling it. Is that correct?
>> Yeah. So it means things like equipment
has to be cleaned. It has to be
sanitary. you know, uh, you can't go to
the bathroom and then just start
processing. You have to wash your hands
in between, gloves, like, you know, all
of those standard things that you think
of from a safety standpoint when
something is ingestable.
questions.
>> Your mic is muted, Chris.
>> Seeing no other comments or questions
for section seven, I'm going to go ahead
and ask for a consensus vote to approve
that section and move on to section
eight. So if you approve of section 7,
please raise your hand.
At present, we have six hands up. Seven.
>> Everybody go ahead and lower your hands,
please.
And is there
>> okay
>> anybody dis dissenting to that to the
approval of section 7.
Seeing no dissent, I'll see that was
approved by consensus
and or by vote rather and we'll move on
to section A talking about labeling
packaging traceability. So section A
says all packages need to be sealed and
labeled
and we're going to go into the rabbit
hole on labeling I'm sure. Um
so the next elements are the required
label elements
and the label must be printed or fixed
on the product package and must include
uh all required information in a legible
font at least eight points be in English
though it may be provided in other
languages be obstructed and unobstructed
and clearly visible the producers's
business name and permit number the type
of product
for example homogenized fungi,
the species name of the fungi. Um, and I
think I might want to add
uh something right off the bat to that,
Dominic. Maybe the cultivar of the fungi
as well.
>> So, make that species and cultivar.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
The net quantity of contents using the
metric system of measurement. The
potency of psilocybin
analytes contained in the product
expressed in milligrams and calculated
using laboratory test results. Total
potential silosin reported report both
or one TPP or TPE total psilocybin
equivalent or total potential silosin
dosage and administration went with
total potential silosin overwhelmingly
that's what they did both or in Colorado
as well I've heard a lot of feedback
from both Colorado and Oregon that is
causing a lot of confusion so that may
be a topic for discussion
A logo designed and provided by the
department that notifies a reasonable
person that the product contains
psilocybin that is no smaller than a/
inch by half inch. A unique
identification number of the product lot
and the state track and trace system
number or identified
identifier associated with the product.
the expiration date
and
are we missing something there?
>> Uh and then it's uh the statements which
basically are the risk benefits, drug
interactions and effects of psilocybin
are not fully understood. Individual
results may vary. Uh statement saying
keep out of the reach of children and
the statement do not drive a motor
vehicle or operate machinery while under
the use of psilocybin.
So basically your your usual warning
labels.
>> Should we add something on here that
packaging cannot be um you know targeted
towards kids or something like like
they've done with tobacco and marijuana.
>> I don't think that's necessary at this
time. And the main reason is because
remember this is going directly from the
producers to the clinical settings or
the therapeutic settings. And so it's
not like cannabis. It is or unlike
cannabis. It's not something people will
be able to buy in a dispensary and bring
home. There'll be items that have to um
you know that are coming through that.
So similar to a doctor's office
>> and remain locked up. Okay.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> All right. So, let's go ahead and talk
about sections A and B.
What are our thoughts?
>> And the only other aspect I'd like to
say, Chris, before we get into it is um
as people can notice in the chat is it
also has section C, which is a product
information document, which has a lot
more information. We're really trying to
ensure that um uh that it is one of
those situations where you don't get a
CVS receipt uh to name a particular
company. Um but uh that it's not
suddenly you're getting a couple of
capsules or a satchet with your dosage
in it and along with it you get a three
miles worth of paper that is just
labeling this. So it's really about
trying to keep this uh smaller um uh so
that the you know on that portion and
then other information that an
individual would want could be done on
the product information document which
can be done electronic so that we're
using less paper and killing fewer
trees. Um and so that's part of the idea
on it. Um, and so just remember and keep
that in mind because we're not talking
about large packages to begin with
regardless with regard to this. And I do
see uh in the comments there uh uh
rewarding a little bit from Greg, we can
definitely look at that. And Estavon,
when you're saying white label program,
what do you mean regarding that? Oh,
unique branding. Yeah, I think unique
branding would be allowed. I that's not
a problem. It's not a situation of this
needs to be black and white label. Is
that what you're asking? Okay. Thumbs
up. Okay. Thank you. Yeah.
>> So, and I think as far as Gregory's
comment that the alkaloids would we
could probably put on the product
information document, I would like to
see the the basic label elements be as
bare minimal as possible. That way we
don't overwhelm people with too much
information and they don't read any of
it. Um,
that would be my thought on that. They
want deeper dive into full test results
that could be attached to the product
information doc.
>> Right. I would agree. And that would be
a part of the results of all laboratory
tests.
Oh, formatting a little messed up there.
A and the the results of all laboratory
tests are actually um on uh inc. And
just to answer Lisa um that is a
conversation that has occurred
previously and the program is not
limiting particular uh cultivars or
species.
>> All right. Um, should we I guess I I'll
I'll go ahead and read C as well and D
just so we can close this uh section out
and then come back and look at it
section by section. Um, so product
information document. A product
information document must be available
that lists the following information in
English on a printed or electric
document in 12point font or larger. All
of the requirements for the product
label. A statement regarding the number
of years the business has been
established in New Mexico and a
statement declaring the state and
country of residency including the
length of time of the primary investors.
Results of all laboratory tests
conducted on the homogenized batch data
homogenization.
The type and composition of the growth
medium used including type of grain,
soil, compost, pesticides and other
inputs.
Dates, date of manufacturer or
processing of the final product. List of
all active and inactive ingredients in
descending order of predominance by
weight or volume.
Why is this a a bullet dominant?
It should just be homogenized fruing
body of mushroom, right?
Right. But there could potentially be
other ingredients uh that are in there,
but it should not be more.
>> Okay. Growth medium used. List of
potential major food allergens which
might be contained in the product or in
the growth medium.
Identity of the intended use and
directions for use. And a description of
of how the product should be stored. the
following statement. This product is not
approved by the FDA to treat, cure, or
prevent any disease. FDA has not
evaluated this product for safety,
effectiveness, and quality. There may be
a long-term adverse health effects from
consumption of psilocybin, including
additional risk for women who may become
pregnant or are breastfeeding. The New
Mexico Poison and Drug Information
Center phone number.
Section D, traceability tracking.
Utilize online tracking system as
required by the department. End to end
batch tracking from cultivation through
final product product. Steps for grow,
harvest, processing, testing, transport,
sale. Uh records retained for a defined
regulator regulatory period of 5 years.
Okay.
So please, what are your thoughts on
section 8 in its entirety?
And just in the chat for those who
aren't able to see it, uh I did put that
section D for the traceability as well.
And James had a question about whether
the DOH producers would create an
example label. And yes, there would be a
sample label. Um
I don't see any other Oh and uh John had
uh actually put uh for example as far as
other items that might be in uh the
medication would be the capsule for
example.
>> Very well. Thank you.
>> Again shouldn't be much.
>> All right.
any and and just to let everybody know,
you know, we've really tried on this,
we've had some uh internal conversations
as well. for example, some of the
statements for the label just due to a
room issue and to create a smaller label
of moving uh some of those statements
onto the product information document
rather than leaving those um on the
label itself. The one that we have sort
of been very clear that needs to stay on
the label no matter what. Um and it's
more from a safety warning standpoint is
the keep out of reach of children. um
leave that on the label regardless, but
potentially move the others onto the in
product information document.
>> Any thoughts on the label? Denali?
>> Yeah, and and sorry, maybe you can fill
me in on previous conversations. I I'm
grateful to hear there's consideration
of, you know, what the burden will be on
um folks who are preparing that just
with how long that is. I I just in
general a lot of these things are about
informed consent which really is the
responsibility of the facilitator. And
so I want to be sure as much as we're
wanting to provide consumer information
on the product really that
responsibility should lie in the
training and education and care protocol
with uh the the requirements that we
adopt around informed consent.
I agree. But uh the I think the
facilitators also need to be aware of
all this to provide or to educate and
receive informed consent.
>> But uh and Chris, I just
>> can I just ask this the medication the
document that's separate from like what
is going to be required on individual
packaging? Is that am I understanding
that right?
Yeah, that that is correct, Denali. But
and what I've done because you you rais
a good point and we actually have uh
mentioned to make sure that that's
there, but we did not have that as a
bullet point here in this outline. And
so I just added in uh under the main
part with um the packaging ensure the
facilitator provides this information uh
and I was typing it as I started talking
um for the label and the what are we
calling it again? I'm sorry. The product
information document
>> and they need to provide that to the
client. Correct.
>> Yes.
>> Right.
>> Is that clear in there or
>> Sorry. Um I'll get it here in just a
moment. Just having a typing issue.
I'm putting it in the chat just so
everyone can see it for those who aren't
seeing it on screen.
>> That was a good catch, Denali. Thank
you.
>> Yes. Thank you, Denal.
>> Other other comments, concerns about
this section?
Okay. Does this committee have a
preference towards total potential
silosin total psilocybin equivalent?
Is this Am I alone on this rock
>> in space?
>> Chris.
>> Oh, go ahead. Let I defer to public
comment on it first. [laughter]
>> Go ahead, Greg.
>> Greg, you should your mic should be
enabled.
>> You said everything without a mic.
Sorry about that. Um
I think
although it is not necessarily this
committee's decision, I think the
influence of our voice can be in
conversation with the bigger picture. I
don't think it's going to be difficult
to include both silosin equivalent and
psilocybin equivalent. And I think that
that might be the best way to go. Um I
have a good visual example of how that
could look if um I can put that in the
chat. Um but I think you know I think we
just kind of table that for now.
>> Yeah. that. So having both scares me
more than one or the other
because I feel like that increases the
chance for confusion. But go ahead,
Dominic.
>> Well, I I was actually Greg actually
said pretty much what I was going to say
because these are about formula and
we're actually already asking in the
testing section for all of these tests
to be done that actually make up both
formulas and it's just a formula at this
point in time. um we could move forward
with having both on there. We also do
have uh the provision that the
department can uh reduce things if they
are found to not be necessary. So for
example, some of the testing and we
could put that in as well on the label.
Therefore, we don't have to go back
through a rule hearing if something is
deemed not necessary at that time. And
then that could still leave the decision
on whether TPP the total potential
psyosin or total psilocybin equivalent
for the dosing and dosage committee to
make that determination.
>> Does that make sense?
So, you're saying just just leave both
of them on there for now and uh then we
can
>> because both of them are really just
formulas based upon the test results,
the potency test results. And so we
could leave them both for now and then
based upon what the dosage committee
comes up with then um then we could
actually the department could say
whichever one does not make it for the
dosage requirement we could then remove
at that time.
>> Okay. Should we change the document just
to say the dosage
per in milligram per gram or leave it
open for both of them on there?
>> I I would leave that open at this time.
>> Okay. Gregory, did you have another
>> um I just exa almost exactly what
Dominic said with an asterisk um
deferring this language so that the
ruling body like defines like so
whatever is defined by whatever is going
to be the language. Um the thing that I
I think I saw Dell in here and I don't
know if uh Dan is here today or anybody
else who's from testing in other states.
Um
many states and many testing facilities
post total alkyoids and that does
include or total alkyoid content and
that does include the miners in the way
that they calculate that up but I would
love somebody from that expertise to
speak on that matter. I think
if we keep it psilocybin and psilocin
equivalency with the minors being
measured separately, I just want to make
sure we sanit san like have sanity
around that u conversation if that makes
sense.
>> I think we're testing them individually.
So based on what I see in this document,
we would
um put the results of all laboratory
tests on the back. And so we would have
individual results for silos and
psilocybin and the three other alkalides
that we're testing for all reported
separately on that product information
document. Um
is does that answer your question, Greg?
That's how I'm reading this.
We have another question there by James
Blackford.
>> James, go ahead.
>> Um, so we can put a pin in this. This is
kind of like a a side question, but um
uh it was briefly spoken upon is as far
as dosage and it uh you know uh each
patient each facility may be different
but is there going to be like a
standardized dosage cuz I know as far as
the growers uh when we are putting them
in capsule form you know measuring out
the milligrams in each capsule you know
is that be inventory we order and stuff
like that to do that specifically and
then if it if the standard is a
different dosage um is there anything
around that to kind of let growers know
you know what to expect what um yeah
that that that's my question if that
needs a a pin in it that's fine
>> I think that's still to be determined
through the dosage committee and the
advisory board so we're going to work on
that um I don't I don't know the answer
to that honestly but That is something
good to keep in mind that uh you know
whatever we
whatever dosages or dosing strategies we
come up with uh assuming we do we need
to relay that information to the lowest
level and it also brings up something
else I've heard from lessons learned in
Colorado that you know
if we
are going to sell this in one unit of
measurement, dose it in another, and
store it in another. That also creates a
lot of confusion. So maybe some
parallelism as far as how we are
um
what unit we are working in throughout
the entire process. And I'm not sure if
this would be the best place to start
that pro that conversation, but um like
if we're gonna
work in silosin, then everything should
be done in milligrams of silosin uh or
you know or psilocybin.
Go ahead, Greg.
uh we don't need to spend much time on
this but I think from a sales point gram
weight of pro of biomass is how you're
going to sell it and the facilitator can
decide how much of that biomass based on
the information on the packaging they
provide to their their people
like the dosage is because this is being
given to a person by a facilitator but
that is under the system is being given
those decisions get through their risk
profile assessment.
Does that make sense?
I don't want to start selling it based
on solosin equivalency. I don't think
that's a good idea.
>> Um, yeah, let's continue down the list
of how is that your is your name? Oh,
I'm sorry. I'm gonna butcher your name.
Is it Shelly?
I'm thinking if you don't know how to
say it, you're talking to me. It's
Chaye. Looks like
>> Chay. Yeah.
>> Yes. Um, if I if I may just chime in
here. Um,
I wait, sorry, my phone.
Psilocybin analytes. A nice way being
that I'm licensed facilitator in Oregon
and doing it now for a couple of years.
there's very much consistency with
dosing when you measure in the analyte.
Um, it's nice to have also the grams of
weight just so that new facilitators can
wrap their brain around
that because a lot of people think in
terms of grams. And it's lovely to have
the analyte on there, but I wouldn't use
that as your only measure because it's
it's such a small amount and there's no
consistency with dosing in that realm.
But it's useful information for people
that want to. That's all I have to say.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Let's go to James.
So, so ju just to round off my point and
and as uh the one prior had stated um it
would be total weight and and the
homogenized product in a powdered form
uh if it's essentially cap you know put
in the capsule um those capsules are
different sizes and the weight would be
set in each one. So, um, having kind of
a standard is like a base unit, um, you
know, per 20 mgram capsules or or
whatever it would be would be good
because if a grower, you know, produces
this end product, capsulates everything,
say at a a 20 milligram weight, um, you
know, seals it and and its final
product, and then it's like, uh, well,
you know, it's going by 0.25 25
milligram and and stuff like that. And
so so I I guess that was my point. Um uh
to to maybe have some kind of standard
as far as like the the base uh metric as
far as what
that would look like.
Yeah, I understand what you're saying.
I'm just not sure I can
we can decide that. That seems like
something more for the dosage committee
if they're going to do,
you know, a standard dosage
unit and
that would be with increases. you know,
I mean, my perspective on that is dosage
is very individual and we shouldn't be,
you know, kind of dictating what those
dosages are on
either side of the range. Um,
but but I don't know. I'm only one part
of this cog. So,
um,
okay.
Coming back to what we need on our label
elements. Is there do we need to make
any changes to this as far as
putting a unit that these need to be
measured in or are we going to sell it
in grams, dose it in milligrams
and
store it in kilograms?
It sounds reasonable to me, but I guess
there has been issues.
All right, let's see. What was that
comment?
>> And [clears throat] and just uh so James
just commented milligram per capsule
with total weight per package. And that
actually does really fall under the net
quantity of contents using the metric
system. Um and so it is pretty
consistent with regard to that. And then
also have the potency. And so what I
think James's concern is, and please
correct me if I'm wrong, James, is that
you don't want to necessarily see that
one producer is for example doing in
milligrams per gram while another is
doing gram per gram type of a thing. And
I think that uh that will very quickly
actually even out regardless of what we
do regulation wise on the label and is
really going to be based upon what the
dosage committee recommends as far as
for dosages and uh dosage range ranges
if that makes sense.
Not seeing any more comments from James.
>> Okay.
>> Great is commenting to motion to adopt
the language.
>> All right. Do is everybody comfortable
or I think everybody seems comfortable
uh adopting
section 7 or section 8 rather in its
entirety. See thumbs up from everybody.
Are we good with this?
Got one, two,
three,
>> four.
>> Right.
>> Okay.
>> Is anybody opposed to section seven or
section 8 as it is?
Estavon, what's your question?
>> Thank you, Chris. This is just regarding
the the traceability section on section
B.
>> Ah, yes.
>> Uh, yeah, within that section there, um,
utilizing online tracking system as
required by the department. Um, I'm sure
that's something that's still up for
discussion potentially. I would just
hate to pigeon hole us into, you know,
requirement that we all have to use one
proprietary software and, you know, it's
5,000 bucks a year, whatever the fee may
be for it. Um, so I think that would
just merit some more discussion perhaps.
>> Okay. Um,
so and you guys ran into this with
cannabis, didn't you, Dominic? So, so
here is the issue with regard to it is
um you know as we move forward looking
at systems uh one of the requirements
that we have always done from the
medical side is that whatever tracking
system is required that they're the
elements that are required by the
department have to be offered free of
charge to the um the end users. So in
this case the producers and the clinics
um and um so that they wouldn't have it.
Now they the system that we use
currently for example does also then
have sort of a pro version that has
additional bells and whistles um that
people can purchase but uh that's not
something that is required but the
actual tracking aspects of it uh which
include point of sale by the way um they
do have to offer that at a no charge to
um the dispensaries uh and again that
was as it was operated under the
department when the department was
operating those aspects of the cannabis
program and we would be doing a similar
situation with regard to this.
>> I hope that answers that Estbon.
>> That was a good catch upon and it sounds
like he's satisfied with that.
>> Yeah. And just to give you an idea, so
like some of the add-on programs, they
do things where um for example, they'll
then track other aspects. You can do uh
other fancy things like doing emails out
to your uh to your clients and your
sales folks. But again, that's a very
different system because you're looking
at a dispensary model, not at a clinic
therapy based model where things are
going out um specifically to those
patients individually. Um and that is
actually something that we would look at
from a functionality standpoint, being
able to message with patients. So,
similar to if you're at your doctor's
office or hospital system where you have
that ability to um you know to reach out
to them through their online portals, we
would have something similar to that.
>> Excellent. Okay. So, uh again I'm going
to open it up to descent for section 8
labeling packaging traceability
tracking.
Any descending voices?
Excellent. We'll call section 8 uh
approved by consensus.
Now that I've got my afternoon spam call
in the middle of the meeting, we'll move
on to section nine.
Um compliance
uh compliance authority the department
uh New Mexico department
>> oh that's a department of agriculture
>> agricultural okay agriculture for
applicable permits local building and
health departments inspectors for local
permits clear corrective action pathways
prior to license suspension or
revocation
um
I'm assuming that'll be handled through
the department of health Right.
>> Yes. And some of those are fairly
standard and so uh with regard to it and
so just to give an idea and please
forgive me if I don't have the days
correct um the number of days I mean um
so for example uh essentially if we were
for example to go and do a site visit at
a location and we were to find um a cat
was wandering around on the processing
tables where uh products were being
homogenized. The department would then
issue a notice of contemplative action
is what they're called. Um and
essentially what we would do is that
particular permade would then have so
many days to be able to correct it and
submit documentation showing that they
have corrected that violation. Um and
once they do then things move forward.
If however they say, you know, the uh
the permites says no, that's not
something that actually happened. Your
inspector when they came in was seeing
cats when there were no cats. Um and
they could actually appeal it and so
there would be an entire appeal process
so that they could go through that. Um
and uh and go through that sort of
portion with that. Um and and the reason
for that is we need to make sure that
that's very clear so that everybody
involved um sees all of those steps in
it and that they see what are the
potential actions on it. Um and and of
course the the final portions of that
would be if indeed yes there were cats
in this particular situation it was not
cleared by the permittee then the
permittee could potentially have their
permit suspended andor revoked at that
point if they don't clear those kind of
violations and um but it has to be a
very clear process saying you have this
amount of time so for example 30 days to
clear that issue but within 10 days they
have to appeal it say no the cat was
never there and then if they do that
then it is revisited. There also has to
be uh the availability of there being a
potential hearing. So for example prior
to the actual suspension uh or
revocation of a license they have the
right to a hearing and that is done with
hearing officers uh that the department
arranges for and uh to make sure that
that's very open and um and clear with
everybody who is involved.
And so that's just that process if that
makes sense. And hope I didn't confuse
it with bringing in the cat. [laughter]
I actually say that because that was an
actual situation that happened years ago
in the can cannabis world.
>> Yeah, everybody loves cats anyway. So I
think you caught their attention.
>> Everybody loves cats. I should have just
put one up on the screen instead of the
documents.
>> James, let's hear your comment, please.
I sorry I I just meant to do a thumbs up
that yes, everybody loves cats. I I hit
the wrong button [laughter]
and I like uh Gregory's comment. Uh
shout out to the Shreddingers box. Yeah,
it's Greg. Um
any any issues with compliance section?
Okay, this seems pretty straightforward.
Um seeing no comments, concerns,
questions, or or recommendations,
I'll go ahead and look for consensus.
Again, please give us a thumbs up if you
approve for section 9.
All right, I'll allow room for descent.
Anybody descent of section 9.
Okay, we'll call that uh adopted by
consensus
and we'll move on to section 10.
Future expansion and review framework
designed to be scalable periodic review
for scientific developments, public
health data and operational performance.
Um, you know, I think Dominic and I have
had this conversation several times that
this is a ongoing process and u we'll
probably be working on this for years to
come. So, or we will be working on this
for years to come. So, [snorts]
um, any comments, concerns with section
10?
Anything else we should put in there?
Yeah. And Chris, we don't actually need
to vote on that because that's really
just saying this is what we need to
ensure we continue doing moving forward.
>> Okay, good to go.
>> Um, but I do have one area that we
realized um just the other day is not
actually in here and I' I'd like to just
um actually ask the committee for a
little bit of indulgence. and and what
it is is transportation
and it's the transportation of the
product from the producer to uh the
therapist uh facilitator therapy center.
Um, and what we really are are looking
at with regard to that is really just
saying that look, it needs to be uh
transported by, you know, people who are
doing so safely. And so making sure it's
in a locked box, for example, that the
person who is transporting it doesn't
make a bunch of stops on the way. So,
for example, you don't want someone
who's driving uh the medication from the
producer to the um to the clinic. You
don't want them stopping off at
7-Eleven, for example, and suddenly
their vehicle gets stolen because they
left it unlocked or that the box that
it's locked up in inside is not secured
to the vehicle and so somebody just
reaches in the open window and grabs it
and um you know uh and so they end up
losing their medic the medication. And
so we if if it is okay with everyone
here, we'll actually develop that to add
into the rules just to ensure that
transportation is done under safe and
secure manner.
Would that be acceptable?
Yeah, I have gotten some feedback from
people in Colorado and given that this
is a rural state, um there's been
um
I guess concern that and you know some
of the producers are having to drive
really long distances to deliver their
product. Uh so one of the
recommendations was that they were able
to meet with other handlers. You know
the facilitators
at some determined place and do
transfers. I don't know how the
department feels about that. Um but it
was something I had to take in
consideration given you know where we
might be trying to get these products
throughout the state. Uh is that Gregory
with your hand up?
Yes, it is. Um I would just like to
voice a preference or or perspective of
in the heart of everything that we've
kind of done in regulation um mitigation
to
during this first phase reduce the kind
of chain like let's not include chain of
custody or like transfer manifests and
stuff like that so we can loosen like
who can and just like keep the
recommendation as safe and secure as
possible. Um, and that would allow for
pickup that would allow for drop off and
meeting and stuff like that. Um, I don't
know how detailed your um,
structure will come out, but yeah, like
I think leaving it in the spirit of what
we've done so far for other regulations
would be nice um, as we ramp up. That
way we don't need transportation
companies.
>> Thank you, Greg. Uh regardless, I will
tell you right now because it's a
schedule one, we would need that from a
legal perspective to have a chain of
custody. But we can easily uh write it
so that it does have other individuals,
whether it be contractors, facilitators,
that sort of thing, who could either
meet up or pick up themselves uh for
that transport.
>> Awesome. Thank you.
Is this going to be an extra required
permit? Do we need to add that to any of
our other sections?
>> I don't think it needs to be an extra
permit, especially if it falls within
either um the uh the current permit
system that we're sort of doing. So, a
producer could do it and we can ensure
that we add that on in for that
facilitator uh wellness center, whatever
they end up being named when when the
committee meets on that. we can ensure
that that same language is there so that
those individuals could and we can
ensure there's language with regard to
contractors
which would mean someone else. So uh for
example if uh you know uh we were
transporting it and uh whether it be the
facilitator andor the producer who hired
a third party to do it as long as they
met with the regulatory requirements so
keeping it safe and secure it would be
acceptable.
And that's actually where the chain of
custody manifest form protects them.
Okay, Gregory.
>> Uh just like earmarking a much later
conversation for the LEA interface
around all that and how those
protections and like
how the legal part of that stuff stands
to protect the transport uh entity. But
not today.
Okay. Any other concerns around
transportation?
And so is this the language you're going
to use or you are we just using this as
a you do is going to kind of create the
language based on this little verb here.
will create the language based on the
blur.
>> Okay?
>> Because remember all of this this is
really the outline for the
recommendation and but the specific
language goes through our legal and all
of that to make it look look uh
regulation standards
>> regally.
>> Yeah. Regula regulatory I don't even
know what word I could make up to make
it sound right. um but to do that um
because there are certain uh ways things
have to be written, language that's used
in order to make sure that it's clear
and that we don't run into issues
because as we've sort of noted before,
commas can make a big difference in how
something reads.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Um let's look for consensus on
transportation. All approved, please
give me a thumbs up. All in favor?
Three. Four.
Four. I'll be five. Any anybody opposed.
Okay. We'll go ahead and uh approve
transportation.
Uh we already decided or
um talked about not needing to approve
section 11.
And uh that brings us to section 12. Are
we going to go into these um
definitions?
>> So here, Dominic, or what's your
recommendation on that? How we handle
this? I would recommend we don't really
need to go into the definitions because
again this is something that with our
legal team or our attorneys they'll
actually go through to make those
decisions. We can provide them with this
so that they ensure that the definitions
do meet with um what is needed. Um I
would say we don't need to go through
each of these. Um I know I've read
through them and overall they seem very
clear. Um, and I'll put the definitions
into the chat. Um, just realize that
again our legal
team may change some of the language a
little bit or add in uh language where
necessary and needed,
>> but I don't know that we need to have a
a vote specifically on definitions.
>> Okay. if um perhaps we should just go
through them since we have the time and
make sure that we're
um we're all in agreement with these. I
don't think we ever talked about them.
So, uh facility means any building space
or grounds licensed for cultivation,
harvesting, drying, storage,
preparation, psilocybin producing fungi
or psilocybin products and subject to
inspection and regulated by the
department. If anybody's got any
comments or questions, just raise your
hand. Um, harvest means the act of
removing psilocybin producing fungi from
a production environment for drying,
processing, or storage. Lot means an
identified portion of a batch that is
uniform and intended to meet
specifications for identity, strength,
purity, composition. I don't think we
used lots anywhere before. Um should we
remove lot?
>> Uh we actually are going to use lot to
help differentiate. Uh and I would just
say it's um because you do have that
between a batch and a lot. But this
actually does not have a definition of
batch in it. I was actually just writing
that in the chat to James.
[laughter]
That's is actually up earlier in uh the
other section talking about that
definition of a batch. So um and again
this is not a comprehensive list. This
is just some ideas.
>> Okay.
Um
specifications for identity, strength,
purity and composition and that may be
subject to testing, quarantine or
recall. License premises means specific
facility or facilities identified in a
producers's license application and
approved by the department within which
the producer is authorized to conduct
regulated activities. Um I feel like
that should be permitted premises since
we're not using licenses
but I could be wrong.
>> Yeah.
No, you're correct.
>> Okay. Producer means a person or entity
licensed by the department to cultivate,
harvest, dry, store, and prepare
psilocybin producing fungi or psilocybin
products for authorized transfer within
the medical psilocybin program. Um,
didn't we determine these were separate
permits and should they have separate?
No, it was going to be one permit with
the the different um
abilities within it.
>> So all of them will have
>> right
>> those Okay, good to go.
Produce or production means to engage in
any activity related to the cultivation,
harvesting, drying, storage or
preparation of psilocybin producing
fungi or psilocybin products.
Psilocybin product means psilocybin
producing fungi, mcelium or preparations
derived there from that are intended for
patient use and contain a detectable
amount of psilocybin or psilocin.
Recall means an action taken to remove a
psilocybin product from distribution or
use after the discovery of
contamination, mislabeling, or other
condition that may pose a risk to
patient safety.
Release of transfer means the point at
which a psilocybin product has satisfied
applicable testing and quality assurance
requirements and may be transferred to
another permitted entity.
Segregate means to separate and withhold
from transfer or use a batch or lot of
psilocybin producing fungi or psilocybin
products pending testing, investigation
or corrective action.
And testing means laboratory analysis of
psilocybin producing fungi or psilocybin
products for potency identity. Um we're
not checking identity, right? And the
presence of contaminants conducted by a
laboratory approved or permitted by the
department.
I'm going to take identity out of there.
Or maybe I won't.
I got it. Maybe you will.
>> Maybe you will. [laughter]
>> Um, and then there was a recommended
strike mycelium from psilocybin products
because we determined that we're not
using mycelio biomass. Yep. Excellent.
Looks like we already done that.
>> Awesome. All right. So, we have a little
bit of time left. I would like to at
this time open it up for discussion uh
or questions about you know
um things that we've already talked
about and
uh also perhaps other proposals that
we've missed in this document.
Uh James has a really good um point um
just uh in the chat just as far as the
size of the capsules and the purchasing
of them as far as the cost of that and
the equipment and and I think James
that's going to be determined over the
next few months. I think before we get
to the point where um uh you know uh
cultivators and producers are going to
have to decide and make a decision on
those, we'll have at least the guidance
with regard to that pretty well in hand.
They're moving they're moving forward
with that as well because I think that's
a really great question and it's a
really great thing to consider. Um and
uh and it does actually affect and
impact some of the cost. So I think
that's a good idea for it.
Yeah, and I understand your concern,
James. I'm not trying to blow you off. I
I just don't have an answer for you yet.
We have to something we have to decide
couple levels first. So,
uh, are there any other questions about
the document in its entirety?
Um,
Dominic, can you remove the note, the
highlighted note, since we've gone
through and approved this entire
document at this point? All right. So,
what I foresee happening next is I'll
take this to the advisory board and we
will
um
present it to them on the 27th.
Hopefully, some of you will be watching
in. I'm not sure how Ian's going to run
it, but I I don't know that there's
going to be opportunity for public
comment like there is in committee. Um,
[clears throat] and uh, we'll go through
through it kind of like we did in here
and hopefully get this approved so
Department of Health can start making
the rules or legal ease out of all of
this. Um, and then following that
process, Dominic, correct me if I'm
wrong, there'll be time for public
comment on the actual written rules,
right? Mhm. So, so just so everybody's
has an idea of how the process works is
once the board has actually said yes to
the recommendations or changed them,
edited them, all of that, we will
actually take them and we're already
starting to work on the drafts of them
on some of the other sections that have
already been uh you know uh already had
approval through this. And so what we
will be doing is uh after that point and
we're hoping fairly quickly um because
it is our primary uh our primary task
right now uh from the department
standpoint is that we will get those
draft rules all set. We will uh we have
to submit them to the registar or sorry
not the registar the New Mexico
registry. Um, can you tell I've been
dealing with some school items lately as
I'm thinking about registars but anyway
we uh work with the New Mexico registry
and we publish with them and when we
publish with them that includes a link
to the those rules and so then from the
date of publication until the rule
hearing there is a minimum of 30 days.
And so once that gets scheduled then the
30 days people can make public comment
during that time period. At the rule
hearing itself what will then occur is
uh there's a hearing officer. We
essentially present the rules and then
the hearing officer opens it up to the
public for any additional public
comment. Um and then the hearing officer
will set a deadline for any additional
uh written comment. Usually it's a
couple of days after the hearing itself.
Sometimes if there's not been very much
public comment, they may do it the end
of that business day or the end of the
next business day. But that is up to the
hearing officer. And then um once that
occurs, the hearing officer then creates
a report, get brings that back to the
department. If there are no major
changes to be made except for, for
example, if there's a few typos or uh
something else that just needed minor
clarification, then the rules can be
promulgated. Promulgated means they're
published and then they go into effect
on publication. If there are major
changes that need to occur that were not
addressed during the rule hearing then
at that point in time uh we have to go
through potentially go through a
secondary rule hearing and it follows
that same process. Um but so all of the
rules like I said the draft will be
published there will be 30 days from the
date of announcement of the publication
until the actual rule hearing at a
minimum. Sometimes it's longer time.
That quite frankly depends on the
calendar and the availability of the
hearing officer. Um, but that way people
are able to provide additional comment
if they have other concerns or issues or
questions at that time. I hope that
helps.
>> Yeah. Yes, that helps. Um, let me find
my screen again. Uh and then so that's
the the large scale uh for what I'm
foreseeing for us is that you know I'll
take this to the board. They'll say yes
this looks all looks good. Here's the
next set of questions we have for you
all or you know rework these sections
because we don't think they're safe
enough or uh what other whatever other
questions they come up with. So, we have
a little break here, but you know, this
is a first draft document and, you know,
I imagine quite a bit of it will get
passed through. I know the board, some
of the board members have already taken
a look at it. Um,
but
in likelihood there's going to be more
work to be done. So, uh, I've got two
more meetings set up, hybrid meetings.
one in Albuquerque on the 11th
at West Mesa Community Center. Is that
right, Johnny?
>> Yep, that's right.
>> Okay. and then one on the 18th uh
hybrid, so in person online in Santa Fe,
uh at a location to be determined and
and I will upload
any documents or I'll have Johnny upload
any any documents that kind of go with
those meetings
at um or attach them to the invitation.
Is that right? Or how are you doing that
now? Yeah, we're trying to figure out a
good way to do that. Um, and are still
not super satisfied because um, yeah,
like today um, yeah, I had to just um,
most of you saw like as of you know, a
certain time this afternoon uh, slash
this morning just emailed um, whoever
happened to be signed up already. I'm
trying to figure out a better way that
Teams will let me automatically do
things, but we're currently not
satisfied with finding something that
works.
>> But we'll do our best to get the word
out about topics and discussions prior
to
>> if nothing else, we are emailing it out
to people so that they do have the
documents and uh
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. because uh it's just we keep
running into this issue uh where every
time we think we come up with a
solution, our it says, "Nope, that's a
security risk. We can't do that." So, uh
it sort of limits us a little bit, but
we want to make sure that things are
done correctly. Um James does have in
the chat a ballpark month for permits to
be available if there's no push back.
So, that's a great question, James. If
uh everything sort of falls into place
as we just discussed, there's no major
changes that need to happen once we do
the draft. If that looks really great,
we do the hearing uh and we're able to
promulgate after the first round of
hearings. When that occur or if that
were to occur, we would anticipate it
being in June to July depending exactly
when the dates fall. And and part of the
reason for that is [snorts]
just as you mentioned so that there is
time for the inoculation until harvest
so that everything can be prepared and
ready for patients in December. There is
just just as a note uh on that is some
people have also said that uh you know
the potential for there to be um product
available and medication available for
some of the training sessions and things
like that. But um that's a an issue for
another committee uh at another time. Um
and and I really would encourage
everybody I know you know Chris has said
that you know we get a little bit of a
break and we do at this point or at
least from the committee standpoint
there is um but those in-person meetings
are going to be important because part
of our hope is that we'll have some more
information by those meetings and
they're also even though this first
portion this big heavy lift is now
entering into this next phase um and
we're going to get a little bit of a
Once the rules are promulgated and we
start doing this, that's quite frankly
when we start finding out what things
did we miss, what ideas that nobody has
thought of as some of the initial
permittes start actually going into
production and what kinds of things do
we need to turn around and look at and
potentially adjust within the rules
because we will be adjusting rules down
the road. This is not a oneanddone for
all of that because we want to be
responsive to the program, make sure
that we're able to do things in a way
that are going to be supportive for the
producers, for the patients, for the
facilitators. And so, there'll be some
things that we miss. I I'd like to say
we're perfect. We are not. and um and uh
and as we've seen with Oregon and
Colorado and with other programs, you
know, it's always a period of uh of time
of adjustments. And so, we're going to
have that period of time. And so, we
just ask that everybody also bear with
us because then the end of the day, what
our primary goal is is how do we help
patients, how do we help people, and how
do we do that as a community? And so,
you know, that's going to be the goal.
We're not always going to please
everybody. We're not always going to
have everything in the way everybody
wants, but that truly is the goal and
that is a part of what we're trying to
do. So, please forgive us for mistakes
in advance, but also don't hesitate to
tell us that we've made a mistake. You
know, we we need to know that as well.
So, don't worry about it. You're not
going to hurt my feelings unless you
start calling me names. Then that's a
whole another story. But, uh, you know,
you're not going to hurt my feelings.
You're not going to hurt the team's
feelings if you say, "Look, you missed
the boat on this. we need to figure out
a way to do this differently. That tells
us, you know what, we need to look at
things and how do we change it? How do
we make this better for people?
So, anyway, I'm going to shut up now and
turn it back to you, Chris, but I just
want to thank everybody for all of this.
This is a lot of work. Thank you
everybody and thank Chris especially.
You've been phenomenal in this entire
process. And so, back to you, Chris.
Now, I also want to thank all of you um
for all of your work and there's so many
that haven't uh aren't here today that I
would like to thank as well if you uh
come back and watch this video. And um
yeah, the process isn't over yet, but
hopefully you'll be at the meeting on
the 27th and then uh then I'll get to
see some of you in person here on the
11th. So, thank you all very much.
>> Thank you everyone.